<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Avght considerations to move al men to inqvire and imbrace, with ane earnest affection, the veritie of faith and religion, which onlie is ane, and which onlie bringeth to saluation, amangs sa monie contrarious sectes, as pretendeth to haue ye same. Cvm privilegio</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5633.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124508</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899144</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899144</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150570</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73756)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150570)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1955:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Avght considerations to move al men to inqvire and imbrace, with ane earnest affection, the veritie of faith and religion, which onlie is ane, and which onlie bringeth to saluation, amangs sa monie contrarious sectes, as pretendeth to haue ye same. Cvm privilegio</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Paris?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno M. D. C. V. [1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Worcester College Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150570:1"/>
            <p>AVGHT CONSIDERA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS TO MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VE AL MEN TO IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QVIRE AND IMBRACE, WITH ANE EARNEST AFFECTION, the veritie of faith and religion, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie is ane, and which onlie bringeth to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, amangs ſa monie contrarious ſectes, as pretendeth to haue ye ſame.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the crucifixion of a male figure or Jesus Christ with two other crucified male figures or thieves, and two other figure with halos</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO. ANNO M.D.C.V.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:150570:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150570:2"/>
            <head>AVGT CONSIDERA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONS TO MOVE AL MEN TO INQVIRE AND IMBRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, with ane earneſt affection, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of faith and religion, which onlie is ane, and which onlie bringeth to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, amangs ſa monie contrarious ſectes, as pretendeth to haue ye ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, al men aught co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, vvha hath created men to be parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his eternal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and requireth na vvther thing of thame, but that thay ſuld merite ye ſame be his treu ſeruice, during the tyme of thair peregrination on earth: for this cauſe thay ar iuſtlie debarred from the end of thair creation, and iuſtlie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuged to the aeternal pains of hel, vvha imployeth nocht al the forces of thair ſaul, to try and knau, vvhat ſort of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150570:3"/>hath the treu ſeruice of God; and vvhaefter kuanledge thairof, imbraceth nocht the ſame, amangs ſa monie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarious ſectes of religion, as in this age praetendeth to haue the veritie thairof. <hi>VVhat ſal it profit a man (ſayeth our ſaneour) if he conqueis al the warld,
<note place="margin">S. Mat, 10. Verſ. 20</note> and tyn his ſaul? what ſal he guie in change for his ſaul? The ſone of man ſal cum in the glorie of his father, and ſal than ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der to euerie ane, according to his works.</hi> This reuard is ather the aeternal glorie of heauin, or the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual pains of hel. In the glorie of heauin ſtandeth menis aeternal felicitie, and in the pains of hel, conſiſteth euer leſting miſerie.</p>
            <p>The ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, that ye treu ſeruice of God is preſcryued be treu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that this treu religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is onlie ane:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4 Verſ. 4.</note> for (as S. Paul ſayith) <hi>thair is onlie ane God, ane faith, ane baptiſme:</hi> Of this it is manifeſt, that amangs ane hundreth contrarious ſectes of religion, euerie ane repugnant to the vvther, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150570:3"/>exponing the bybil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariouſlie, efter thair auin priuat inuentions, and euerie ane accuſing the vvther of hereſie, and adulteringt the vvord of God, <hi>thair is onlie ane treu religion that leadeth to ſaluation:</hi> Thairfor al ye vvthers ar led blindlie in the vvay of perdition, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued throught ane fals praetext of the veritie thairof, be the craft of Sathan, and of his ſuppoſts.</p>
            <p>The third is, that the treu moyen to try and knau ye veritie of religion is, to learne it of the treu church of God, and nocht be thair auin brains, nor be ye doctrine of particuler me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vvha reideth and exponeth the ſcriptures efter, thair auin iugements, and be thair particuler inuentions, or vvha receaueth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſcriptures inuented be priuat men; <hi>for as S. Peter ſayeth:
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. Verl. 20.2.</note> No prophecie, or treu wnderſtanding of the ſcripture, is maid be ane priuat interpretation;</hi> that is to ſay be parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer men, vvho hath no publik charge be lauful promotion in Chriſts vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150570:4"/>church; ſik as vvas frere Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ane particuler monk of the order of S. Auguſtin in germanie, vvha ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ane neu ſect be his particuler ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſcriptures inuented be his brane, vvhich vvas contrarious to the vniforme expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thairof, vvhich the vniuerſal church of God had tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in al ages befor him. Siclyk his Diſciple A Ecolampadius vvas ane par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler and priuat frere, in germanie: And zuinglius vvas ane particuler pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roche preiſt in zuric, vvho inuented ane vvther particuler expoſition of ye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to that of thair maiſter; and ſa he erected ane vvther neu ſect of religion. Caluin lykuayis vvas ane par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler chanon in the toun of Noion in France, and be his auin particuler ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſcriptures, eſtablished ane vvther ſect of religion, different from al the vvthers. Nocht onlie thir, and ſik vvyers particuler ſectes, erreth in maters of religion, follouing thair auin priuat doctrine, and particuler ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150570:4"/>of the ſcriptures to thair aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal perdition; bot alſo, al thoſe vvha leauing and deſpyſing the vniforme doctrine, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſcriptures of chriſts vniuerſal church, teached in al ages thir fyftein hundreth zeares by gane, praecipitateth thame ſelfes hedlongs in the vvay of hereſie, to thair aeternal perdition, if thay perſiſt in the ſame, to the end of thair lyfes. Seing than, that <hi>the veritie of religion can nocht be learnit be the doctrine of priuat men, whainterpreteth the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as S. Peter ſayeth, to thair auin perdition:</hi> Thairfoir the onlie treu moyen to knau, ye veritie of religion is, to learne it of the treu church of God, to ye vvhich, Chriſt Ieſus him ſelf referreth the deciſion, and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of controuerſies, ſaying to euerie ane; <hi>dic eccleſiae:
<note place="margin">S. Mat. 18. Verſ. 17.</note> Tel or ſhau to the church;</hi> he pronunceth ane ſentence agains the proud contemners thairof; <hi>that we ſuld eſtime thame, as Pagans and Publicans, wha heireth noch the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150570:5"/>woce of the church,</hi> and repugneth to the determination thairof in maters of religion. This is thane ane infallible reul: <hi>to beliue; as ye church beliueth,</hi> In ſa doing vve can na vvayis erre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus the church of God can na vvayis erre, as is prouen be inuincible raiſons. Firſt, becaus the doctrine of the treu church of God is the doctrine of Chriſt Ieſus,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1 Verſ. 22.3. S. Ih. 14. Verſ. 10. S. I hone Verſ. 13.</note> and of his halie ſpirit, for <hi>Chriſt is the head of the church of God, as S. Paul witneſſeth: And Chriſt promiſed to aſsiſt ye ſame with his holie ſpirit, wha ſuld teach al veritie thair in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuallie wuto the end of the warld.</hi> Secundlie this church, vvhairof he is the head,
<note place="margin">5. Luc. 1. Verſ. 33. Dan. 2. Verſ. 44.</note> 
               <hi>is his kingdom on earth? whith ſal neuer haue ane end, as the ſcripture witneſſeth:</hi> Bot vvhair Chriſt regneth be veritie, Sathan can nocht regne thair in be hereſie. And vvhair Chriſt teacheth al veritie be his holie ſpirit vvnto the end of the vvarld, the ſpirit of errour can nocht teach hereſie thair in at onie tyme: Thairfor it is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150570:5"/>impoſsible that ye treu church of God, vvair of Chriſt is euer the head, and the holie ſpirit the inſtructour in al ages, can erre in onie age to ye end of the vvarld. Thridlie <hi>S.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3 Verſ. 15,</note> Paul calleth ye church, the piller, and ſure ground, or vphald of veritie.
<note place="margin">Mat. 16. Verſ. 16.</note> Fourtlie our ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our affirmeth, that the zettis of hel can nocht preuail agans his church:</hi> Thair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for Sathan can nocht ouercum the church of Chriſt Ieſus be errour. Seing than, that the doctrine of the treu church, is the doctrine of Chriſt, and of his holie ſpirit, in al ages vvnto the end of the vvarld: Thairfor the treu church of God can nocht erre in onie age, vvnto the end of ye vvarld: for this cauſe, <hi>wha beliueth,
<note place="margin">Note.</note> as the church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueth, can na wayis erre; and</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlie euerie ane vvha vvald be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the veritie of religion, ſuld learne ye ſame of the treu church of God, vvhairof Chriſt Ieſus is the head, and nocht of particuler men, vvho teached neu doctrine repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to that of Criſts
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150570:6"/>vniuerſal church in al Aages to thir dayes.</p>
            <p>The fourt conſideration is inferred of the former doctrine, that ſeing the treu church of God can na vvayis erre, be raiſon of the perpetual aſsiſtance of Chriſt Ieſus thairto, and of his halie ſpirit:
<note place="margin">Note.</note> Thairfor <hi>euerie ane aught to try out moſt earneſlie, wha amangs al the profeſſoures of the monifald contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us formes of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ye treu church of God, and adher thairto;</hi> for it is ye onlie shool, vvhair in thay may learne the veritie of religion, that bringeth to ſaluation.</p>
            <p>The fyft co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration is, that the treu church of God, vvhich onlie is tached be Chriſt, and his holie ſpirit, in al ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to the end of the vvarld, may be euidentlie knauen, &amp; decerned, from the malignant churches of deceatful heretiks, <hi>be tua manifeſt marks conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this article of our creid: I. beli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the holie catholik church.</hi> Sa the treu church of God, is yat onlie euoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150570:6"/>and viſible aſſemblee of thaiſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie amangs Chriſtians, vvha ſerueth, and adoreth, God in ane holie ſocietie, and feloship of his treu vvorshipers, conioyned in vnitie of faith and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, diſperſed vniuerſallie throght al ye vvarld, vvhair euer Chriſts holie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is treulie profeſſed. Be this qualities Chriſts treu church is decerned from the viked particuler congregations of heretiks, vvha ar euer in ſynne, and ar contened vvithin the boundes of certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne corners, and particuler dennes of chriſtindome, and remaneth onlie cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan tymes throght hypocriſie for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes, <hi>that the conſtant wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipers of God (as S.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11 Verſ. 19.</note> Paul ſayeth) may be manifeſted be tryal of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and decerned from hypocrites for yis, and vvther cauſes S. Paul ſayeth, <hi>that it is neceſſar that hereſies ſuld be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſext conſideration is, concerning the firſt mark of Chriſts treu church, that it muſt be holie, and that in tua re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpctes firſt in reſpect of holines of lyf.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150570:7"/>Nixt in reſpect of holines, of doctrine. The church of God is called holie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus in it, thair is treu remiſsion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; in no ſect of heretiks: Thair for <hi>S.
<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> Auguſtin</hi> ſayeth, vve may obtene ſaluation in the onlie treu church of Chriſt Ieſus;
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. Verſ. 21</note> and <hi>S. Peter calleth the particuler conuenticles of heretiks, ſectes of perdition.</hi> The holines of Chriſts treu church is proue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in reſpect, that ſum of the members thairof, ar preſerued from al ſpot of deidlie ſynne be ane ſpecial grace and particuler pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of God, vvthers vvha keiping vnitie of faith, and falling in fynne, ar purged thairfra, and maid holie be the verteu of chriſts death and paſsion, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to thame, be his holie ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, This mark conueneth na vvayis to onie of thair neu ſectes of proteſtants; and in particuler it can nocht conuene to thame of Caluins ſect, as is plane be thair auin doctrine; for ye miniſters of thair ſect teacheth, and thair adherent auditoures beliueth aſſuredlie, that it is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150570:7"/>impoſsible to be vvithout deadlie ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in this lyf, or to keip the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: of this it folloueth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarlie, that thay ar nocht of the church of God, vvhich is holie, becaus thay al ar perpetual tranſgreſſoures of the commandements of God, and euer in dendlie ſynne, during thair lyftyme, as thay confes thame ſelfs: Thair for be thair auin confeſsion, thay can nocht be in the eſtait of holines of lyf, ſa lang as thay liue for vvha ar in perpetual ſyn ne can neuer be holie; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, thay can neuer enter in heauin;
<note place="margin">Note. Apoc. 21 Verſ. 27.</note> for <hi>as the ſcripture vitneſſeth; No vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clene thing, or infected with ſynne and vnpurged thairfra can enter in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin.</hi> Be the contrare, the Apoſtolik, and Roman church is holie, becaus ſum of the members thairof ar pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from ſynne, be ane ſpecial gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God, <hi>as the virgin Marie,
<note place="margin">Luc. 1. Verſ. 28.</note> to whom ye Angel Gabriel ſaid: hail ful of grace:</hi> This fulnes of grace culd nocht conſiſt vvith onie ſpot of ſynne.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150570:8"/>Thairfor this glorious mother of God vvas preſerued from al ſpot of ſynne, be ane ſpecial grace of God, to be the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and ſanctified tabernacle of his ſone Chriſt Ieſus; and thairfor he ſayith of hir.
<note place="margin">Cant. 4. Verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Tota pulchra es amica mea, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula non eſt in te. Thou art al beutiful my loue, and thair is nocht ane ſpot in the.</hi> VVe reid alſo, <hi>that S. Ihon the Baptiſt, wha was the forrinner of chriſt was repleniſhed with the holie ſpirit euen from his mothers wombe;
<note place="margin">Luc. 1. Verſ. 15.</note> as the ſame</hi> Angel of God declaired to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Zacharias: Thairfor he vvas pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from ſynne from his mothers vvombe, that he micht be the holie forrinner of his maiſter Ieſus Chriſt S. Luc alſo vvitneſſeth,
<note place="margin">Luc. 5. Verſ. 6.</note> 
               <hi>that S. Ihonis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and mother called zacharias and Elizabeth, war baith iuſt befor God, and walked in al the commandements, and iuſtifications of the lord without reproch:</hi> Of this it is manifeſt, that ſum of the treu church ar holie, in reſpect of holines of lyf, becaus aboue the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150570:8"/>of thair corrupted nature, thay liued ane clein and holie lyf, and keipit al the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of God. That vvthers of the Roman church ar maid holie be purgation from thair ſynnes, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be manifeſt ſcripturs:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50. Verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Firſt we ar conceaued, and borne in original ſynne;</hi> Ve ar clenged thairfra, &amp; reſtored to ane neu and holie lyf, be the ſacrament of baptiſme. <hi>S. Paul vitneſſeth yis ſaying:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5 Verſ. 20</note> Chriſt hath giuen him ſelf for his church clenging, hir be the lauer of wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter in the word of lyf.</hi> This lauer of vvatter in the vvord, <hi>is baptiſme,</hi> vvhich <hi>this apoſtle in wther places,
<note place="margin">Tit 3. Verſ. 20</note> calleth the lauer of regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> becaus be the vvaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hing thair of, vve ar regenerated, that is to ſay, borne agane, be ane ſpiritual birth to ane neu, clein, &amp; holie lyf, and maid ſones of God be adoption,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2 Verſ. 3.</note> vvha be our firſt birth of our earthlie mother <hi>war borne ſones of Ire:</hi> for this cauſe,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3. Verſ. 5 1. Pet. 3. Verſ. 21</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul ſayeth, that God ſaueth was be the lauer of regeneration.</hi> This effect of baptiſme to purge vvs of original
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150570:9"/>ſynne, and to reſtoire to ane holines of lyf, is teached and practiſed in the Roman church, agains the hereſie of thir nouateurs denying that baptiſme hath-onie verteu of Chriſts death to vvash vvs of our ſynnes, and to ſaue vvs, affirming that it is onlie ane ſinge and repreſentation of vvashing: Thairfor this holines of lyf maid be baptiſme is performed conforme to the Roman church be purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes, &amp; nocht efter Caluins doctrine.</p>
            <p>As baptiſme maketh vvs holie pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vvs of original ſynne: Sa the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of penitence, maketh vvs ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, purging vvs of actual ſynne, in ye Roman church, and it reſtoreth vvs to ane inherent and inuard iuſtice, and to ane ſanctified lyf. This is prouen <hi>be S. Peter wha ſayeth to the paenitent Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, wha aſsiſted to the murther of Chriſt:
<note place="margin">Act. 2. Verſ. 28.</note> Paenitentiam agite. Do pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and be euerie ane of zou bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ye name of Ieſus Chriſt for remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of zour ſynnes,</hi> and in ane vvther
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150570:9"/>place he ſayeth.
<note place="margin">Act. 3. Verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Paenitemini &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertimini, vt deleantur peccata ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra.</hi> That is to ſay: <hi>Do pennance, and be conuerted, that zour ſynnes may be tane auay.</hi> The Caluiniſts denying this taking auay of ſynnes be baptiſme, and paenitence, hath peruerted this ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be thair fals tranſlation, for vvhair S. Peter ſayeth. <hi>Paenitentiam agite, Do pennance: thay ſay: amend zour lyfes.</hi> Bot in the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> church be doing of pennance, our ſynnes ar tane auay, ſayeth S. Peter, and vve ar reſtored to ane inuard Iuſtice, and holines of lyf, be treu remiſsion and purgation from ſynnes, &amp; inuard ſanctification. Thair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for the onlie Roman church, is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie treu church of God, becaus it onlie is holie, in reſpect of holines of lyf.</p>
            <p>The Roman church is holie alſo in reſpect of nevv of doctrine, becaus it can neuer erre in maters of faith and religion: <hi>for Chriſt Ieſus regneth be veritie and iuſtice thair in to the end of the warld, and teacheth al veritie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150570:10"/>be his holie ſpirit,</hi> for be him, (as is al readie prouen) he inſtructeth the lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Doctoures of his church in al ages to the end of the vvarld: Of this it is manifeſt, that this firſt mark of the treu church of God, concerning holines of lyf, and of doctrine, conueneth to the onlie Roman church: Thairfor ye onlie Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> church is ye treu church of God, &amp; the onlie immaculat ſpouſe of Chriſt Ieſus, ſeing it onlie, is holie baith in reſpect of lyf and of doctrine.</p>
            <p>The ſeuent conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſecond infallible mark of the treu church of God, in ſa far as it is called catholik, or vniuerſal: It is ſo called for thrie notable reſpectes; In ſa far as it hath vniuerſalitie of tymes, of places, &amp; of perſones,
<note place="margin">S. Aug. de vnita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae.</note> 
               <hi>as S. Auguſtin confirmeth be man feſt ſcriptures agains the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiks of his age:</hi> and proueth be ye ſame that the onlie Roman church is the treu church of God, aga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ye particuler ſectes of ye donatiſts, of ye manichians, &amp; of vvther haeretiks of his age: And vve
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150570:10"/>proue alſo be the ſame ſcriptures, that nather ye neu ſectes of the Lutherians, nor of ye Caluiniſts, nor of ye Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, nor of vvther particuler conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, of vvther nouateurs can be ye treu church of God, becaus thair ſectes hath nather vniuerſalitie of tymes, nor of places, nor of perſones: thairfor ye mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of thir neu ſectes hath erected, &amp; manteneth ſectes, of perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>as S.
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. Verl. 2.</note> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter calleth al neu ſectes,</hi> repugnant to the ancient church of God. Thair ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of ye ſcriptures is natheer of Chriſt, nor of his holie ſpirit, ſeing thay ar nocht members of Chriſts church, vvhich hath vniuerſalitie of places, of tymes, and of perſones as thir ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſcriptures teſtifieth planlie.</p>
            <p>S.
<note place="margin">S. Aug.</note> Auguſtin proueth be ſindrie ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of ye neu &amp; ald teſtament, that ye treu church muſt haue vniuerſalitie of places, and be ſpred amangs al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Amangs ſindrie vvther paſſages, he produceth that ſolemnet promeſſe that God, maid to Abraham ſaying:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150570:11"/>
               <hi>Benedicentur in ſemine tuo,
<note place="margin">Gen. 22. Verſ. 18.</note> omnes gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes terrae, quia obediſti voci meae, al the nations of ye warld ſalbe bliſſed in thy ſeid, becaus thou haiſt obeyed my woce.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 26 Verl. 5.</note> And agane he ſaid: <hi>Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centur in ſemine tuo omnes ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces terrae, eo quod obedierit Abraham voci meae, &amp; enſtodierit praecepta &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>data mea, &amp; ceremonias, legeſque ſeruarit. Al the nations of the earth ſalbe bliſſed in thy ſeid becaus Abraham hath obeyed my voce,</hi> and keiped my praeceptes, and commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ceremonies, and laues. Note heir, that Abraham keiped the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and deſerued ane great reuard to him ſelf, and his poſteritie for the keiping thairof, the miniſters denyeth the ane and the vvther: Bot God heir teſtifieth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trair.
<note place="margin">S. Paul. Gala. 3.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul exponeth this ſeid of Abraham to be Chriſt Ieſus, wha is the ſone of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on his bliſſed mothers ſyd,</hi> in vvhom al nations of the vvarld vvas bliſſed becaus he redemed thame al, be his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150570:11"/>death and paſsion, and called thame to the treu ſeruice of God, in vnitie of his church, vvhich is the greateſt bliſsing that the nations of the vvarld culd ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene: becaus that vvas the onlie moyen to bring thame to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The church of God, befor the cuming of Chriſt, vvas in manifeſt amangs of the Ieues;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 81.</note> Thairfor ye prophet Dauid ſaid. <hi>Notus in Iudea Deus, in Iſrael magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nomen eius. God is knaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Iudeae, &amp; his name is great in Iſrael.</hi> Bot Chriſt at his cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing <hi>took auay ye parpel wal,</hi> vvhich ſeparated the Ieues from the gentiles, vvha vvar than Idolatres; he conioyned thame baith in vnitie of his church be his treu faith; ſa he maid ye church of God catholik, that is to ſay, ſpred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mangs al nations. The ſame learned father proueth this be thir vvords of Chriſt ſaying to his Apoſtles:
<note place="margin">Luc. 24. Verſ. 46</note> 
               <hi>It behu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit Chriſt to ſuffer, &amp; ryſe ye third day from death, and paenitence to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, &amp; remiſsion of ſynnes in his name in al nations, be giuing at Hieruſalem.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150570:12"/>He ſend his Apoſtles vvith pouer and autoritie to eſtablish his church ama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs al nations,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28. Verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſaying to thame go, &amp; teath al nations, baptiſand thame in ye name of the father, and of the ſone, &amp; of the holie ſpirit.</hi> And in ane vvther place he ſayeth to thame:
<note place="margin">Act. 1. Verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>ze ſalbe witneſſes to me in Hieruſalem and in al Iudea, and Samaria, and wnto ye end of ye warld.</hi> Thay executed this charge, as the rayal Prophete ſpak of thame, ſaying. <hi>In omnem terram exiuit ſonus eorum, &amp; in fines orbis terrae verba eorum: The ſound of thair woce paſſed out throght al ye earth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> &amp; thair words paſſed wnto the end of ye warld.</hi> The ſame learned father confirmeth this amplitud and greatnes of Chriſts church, be ſindrie teſtimonies of ye prophetes, &amp; pſalmes vvhairin ye ſpirit of God deſcryued ye greatnes of Chriſts kingdome, vvhich is his catholik church on earth. His father ſaid to him:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Poſtula a me, &amp; dabo tibi gentes haereditatem tuam, &amp; poſſeſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem tuam terminos terrae. Aſk of me,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150570:12"/>and I ſal giue to ye, ye natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be thy heretage, and the ends of the warld to be thy poſſeſsion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 17.</note> And in ane vvther place it is ſaid of Chriſt. <hi>Dominabitur a mari vſque ad mare; &amp; a flumine vſque ad terminos or bis terrarum: He ſal haue dominion from ſea to ſea; and from flude to the ends of the warld, al kinges ſal adore him, al ye trybes of ye earth ſalbe bliſſed in him, al nations ſal magnifie him.</hi> In reſpect of this gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atnes of Chriſts kingdome vvhich is his church,
<note place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel calleth him ane ſtone cutted out of ane montane, without ye hands of men which groueth, &amp; reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth ye earth.</hi> Be thir ſcriptures, and monie vvthers S. Auguſtin concludeth, yat ye treu church of God, mon be vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal in reſpect it is diſperſed throght al ye vvarld: Of this vniuerſalitie he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth, yat ye ſect of ye Donatiſts vvas nocht ye treu church of God, becaus it vvas nocht vniuerſalie diſperſed ama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs al natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; for it exceded nocht ye bon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Africa, but vvas circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcryued vvithin
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150570:13"/>prouinces thairof. Be the force of this inuincible raiſon vve conclud lykuayis agains the Caluiniſts, that thair ſect is nocht the treu church of God, becaus it is nocht catholik or vniuerſal; for it excedeth nocht the bounes of Europ, and is contened vvithin feu prouinces thairof. Thair is nocht ane kingdom in the vvarld, that euer profeſſed this cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſme, but the preſent of Scotland: As for Ingland vvhich appeireth to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie cheiflie vvith it thay differ in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of religion: for thay of Ingland keip holie al the dayis of the concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, natiuitie, circumciſion, paſsion, reſurrection, and aſcenſion of Ieſus Chriſt, and celebrateth thame vvith greater ſolemnitie, nor thay do commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſundayis. Thay ſolemniſe alſo vvitſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in memorie that Chriſt Ieſus ſend his holie ſpirit that day to his Apoſtles, for thair inſtructeur in ye euaugelical lau. Thay keip alſo holie the dayis of Chriſts bliſſed mother, and of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Bot the mineſters of Scotland
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150570:13"/>calleth al thir and vvther points ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and idolatrie, and the miniſters of the clergie of Ingland calleth thir miniſters puritans. The Beshope of London hath vvreatten books agans ye puritans: Thay of Ingland hath alſo thair Beshopes, and Archiebishopes, as prelates, and ſuperiores: The common peple doth reuerence thame in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, crauing thair bliſsing on thair knees; Bot thir miniſters diſpyſeth the gouername<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the church be Bishopes, and Archibeshopes; albeit the king (vvhome God moth ſaue) conſtraneth thame novv to acknauledge the autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Bishopes, and Archibishopes: Thairfor thay of Ingland hath nocht vnitie of faith vvith thame of Scotland. This vvas euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to al thame vvho han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ye churches of baith ye countreyis: Bot ſence God hath exalted our king to the coroune of Ingland, his maieſtie at his entree in that countrey being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued in thair churches be thair bisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes adorned at thair ſeruice, vvith ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150570:14"/>ſtoles, four neuked bonetes, and vvther orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, vvich thay haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued efter the cumlie rite of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik and Roman church; his maieſtie approuing that cumlie &amp; decent order obſerued in thair praetended diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, hath reiected the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed &amp; laical order obſerued be the puritan miniſters of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in thair deformed churches: Thairfor his maieſtie hath embraced ye forme of Ingland: he receaued thair ſacrament vpon his knees, out of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of ane archibishop adorned vvich his mitre, and vvther ornaments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to his dignitie, befor ane coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red altar, vpon the vvhich he layed his offrand vvith great reuerence. The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans of Scotland called this maner of adminiſtration of hair ſacrament, ane Inglish meſſe. According to this order his maieſtie promiſed to reforme the puritan miniſters of Scotland; So vvith tyme thay muſt preach in ſurplices, and four neuked bonets, vvhich thay prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched thir ſourtie zeares bypaſt, to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150570:14"/>the mark of the beaſt, and ſigne of the great Antichriſt. Thay do nou appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue (at the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the keing) the authoritie of Bishopes and Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishopes to be lauful, and conſonant to thair Euangel; vvhich thay preached befor this tyme, vvas vnlauful, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to thair Euangel. Latonie man conſider of this contrarietie, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in cheif heades of religion, of thir Chamelio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſters, importeth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ather vvith thair night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, or amangs thame ſelfes? prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ane thing to be treu this zear, vvhich thay haue preached to be fals yir fourtie zears bypaſt. Of this it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, yat thair caluinian ſect hath nocht vniuerſalitie of places, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequentlie, it is nocht chriſts vniuerſal church.</p>
            <p>The Donatiſts anſuered, that Chriſts church vvas vniuerſel, &amp; ſpred amangs al natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be his Apoſtles. Bot thairefter it decayed, &amp; vvas oppreſſed be errour, &amp; ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; remained in that eſtait euer, vvhil God (is thay fenzied) raiſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150570:15"/>Donatus (of vvhom thay vvar called Donatiſtes) to reforme the vvarld, be preaching the veritie of the goſpel, vvhich vvas extinguiſed befor his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. The Caluinian miniſters vvſeth ye ſame ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bterfuge, ſaying; that ye vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal church vvas oppreſſed be errour, and diſtroyed, be Sathan and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, mairmon ane thuſand zeares, and the veritie extinguiſed be ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Idolatrie, euer vvhil it plaiſed God (as thay fenzie) to raiſe vvp Ihon Caluin, to preach the veritie of Chriſts treu Euangel; Sa it plaiſeth thame to ſtyle the darknes of thair cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinian haereſies. S. Auguſtin refuted the anſuer of the Donatiſts, shauing, that thay ſupponed moſt falſlie, that the church of God vvas or culd be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrauen be errour befor Donatus: Or in onie age to the end of the vvarld: becaus the church of God, muſt be ay vniuerſal in reſpect of vniuerſalitie of tymes: It muſt ſtand victorious in al ages agans al ye enemies thairof, vvnto
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150570:15"/>the end of the vvarld, as he proueth be manifeſt ſcriptures, vvhich vve haue deducet heirto for, vve proue be the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſcriptures, that thir miniſters ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poneth moſt falſlie the defection and decaying of Chriſts church from the veritie of his vvorshiping, or the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion thairof be Sathan and his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts:
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> 
               <hi>for the zettis of hel can nocht praeuail agains Chriſts church as he him aſſurred ws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vniuerſalitie of tymes of the treu church, importeth baith a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiquitie from the Apoſtles dayes; and thairfor it is called Apoſtolik; and alſo it importeth perpetuitie; that it being anis eſtabliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, and planted be the Apoſtles, it ſuld neuer decay nor be ouercumed, and conſequentlie it ſuld remaine viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilie diſperſed throght al the vvarld, and victorious in al ages agans al the enemies thairof: This is prouen be Chriſts infallible promeſſe ſaying, that he <hi>hath builded ſo ſurlie his church vpon ane,</hi> ſtrong and firme rok.
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Portae
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150570:16"/>inferi non praeualebunt aduerſus eam. The zettis of hel ſal nocht praeuail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans hir,</hi> vvha is his immaculat ſpouſe, and of vvhom he ſaid.
<note place="margin">Oſee. 2. Verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Deſponſaui eam mihi in aternum. I haue handfaſt, and eſpouſed hir to me for euer:</hi> Seing the Caluinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth, that thair praetended church vvas ouercumed be ye forces of ſathan, mair nor ane thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand zeares: Thairfor thair pretended church, is nocht ye treu church of God, of ye vvhich Chriſt Ieſus aſſurreth vvs, that ye zettis of hel: That is to ſay, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ſynne, and ſuperſtition, vvhich bringeth to hel, zea al the forces of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than be perſecution ſal nocht praeuail agans his church.</p>
            <p>Thay ar conſtraned to fenzie ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of ye church, becaus vvhan ye ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks aſketh of thame, in vvhat pairt of the varld vvas thair church befor Caluin? Thay can nocht shau onie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or toune in the varld, that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or euer hard vvord of ſik ane reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as thay teach and profeſſe. Thair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150570:16"/>thay ar conſtraned to ſay, that the church of God vvas ſuppreſſed, vvhil thay cam to eſtablish ye ſame. The Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therians praetendeth the lyk, of thair church, vvhan ye Catholiks aſketh of thame, vvhair thair church vvas, befor frere Martin Luther? I hay affirme that the vvarld vvas ouercumed be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, befor his dayis, &amp; that the vvord, vvhich he preached, vvas the onlie ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Chriſts Euangel: And that Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, vvha inuented ane neu doctrine of his auin brane, contrair to his, vvas ane proud heretik, peruerting the Euangel, of Chriſt and his ſacramentes: for this cauſe the Lutherians called the Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, ſacramentaries, becaus thay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted the ſacraments, denying ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie, the real preſence of Chriſts bodie and blood in ye ſacrament of the altar, vvhich ye Lutherians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth. Be this anſuer of the ane, and the vvther, it is manifeſt, that nather of thame hath the treu church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus thay confes, that the zettis of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150570:17"/>hel hath praeuailed agans thair preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded churches: This ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nocht be ſaid of Chriſts treu church: for it is his kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on earth:
<note place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> of ye vvhich ye prophete Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel ſaid, <hi>that it ſuld ſtand for euer, &amp; ouerthral al wther monarchies: And ye Prophet Dauid ſaid:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 144</note> Regnum tuum regnum omnium ſaeculorum, &amp; domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio tua in generatione, &amp; generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem: Thy regne is a regne of al ages, and thy dominion is in al generation to generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.</note> And Chriſt him ſelf promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be vvith his church to the end of the vvarld:
<note place="margin">Iho. 14.</note> &amp; yat in his viſible abſence he ſuld aſsiſt the ſame vvith his holie ſpirit to teach al veritie thairin to ye vvarlds end.</p>
            <p>The third qualitie of the treu church is, that it ſuld be catholik, or vniuerſal in reſpect of vniuerſalitie of perſones, that as it ſtandeth in al ages agans the forces of hel: ſa it muiſt haue perpetual ſucceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lauful Paſtoures, to inſtruct Chriſts viſibil flok, to gouerne ye ſame in peace and vnitie of faith, vvnto the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150570:17"/>end of the vvarld.
<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. Verſ. 11.12.</note> This is prouen be <hi>S. Paul ſaying: Chriſt hath giuen to his church, ſum Paſtoures and Doctoures, for the wark of the miniſtrie, for the building of the bodie of Chriſt; (which is viſible church) whil we be al gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in vnitie of faith:</hi> Bot this gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of al chriſtians in vnitie of faith, vvilbe, maid onlie at the latter day: Thairfor Chriſts church, muſt haue perpetual ſucceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lauful paſtoures, to teach his church, vvnto ye end of ye vvarld: Bot thir properties conueneth na vvayis to Caluins ſect: for vvhan vve aſk of ye miniſters thairof, vvha vvar ye paſtoures of thair church befor Caluin? And vvha teached fik doctrine and interpretation of ye ſcriptures as thay do? ſeing thay refuſe to ſtand be ye interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ye ſcriptures, giuen be al ye antient Doctoures, vvha deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended be lineal ſucceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from Chriſts Apoſtles vvnto our age? Thay can nocht deſigne onie lauful Paſtours or Doctoures, vvith vvhom thay conſent
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150570:18"/>in vnitie of faith and religion in onie age befor Caluin, vvhan vve aſk of tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, to vvhom Caluin ſucceided? or vvha gaue him impoſition of handes? And vvhat lauful prelat and ſuperiour ſend him vvith pouer and autoritie to preach? vvithout ye vvhich pouer and autoritie, no man ſuld be eſtimed ane lauful Paſtour?
<note place="margin">Rom. 10 Verſ. 15.</note> for as <hi>S. Paul ſayeth: hou can thay preach, except thay be ſent?</hi> To this thay ſing dum, becaus it is certan, that Caluin intruded him ſelf in ye cathedral ſeat of geneue, and chaiſed auay ye lauful Beshop thairof, be force of armes, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tening ſum facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous peple of that toune in rebellion, agais thair natiue Prince. Thair com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſubterfuge is, that he vvas called be ane extraordinar vocation, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie be God, to reforme ye vvarld, as vvar ye Prophetes in ye auld lau. This anſuer is ane common ſubſterfuge of al haeretiks, as ye antient Doctoures vviineſſeth; Bot is nocht vvallable, for Chriſt hath promiſed ane perpetual
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150570:18"/>ſucceſsion of laufullie called Paſtoures to his church: Thairfor this extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar vocation hath na place in Chriſts church: Nether is thair neceſsitie (as thay praetend) of extraordinar Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for reformation of the doctrine thairof, becaus I haue prouen, that Chriſts church can neuer erre. Mair ouer S. Paul affirmeth <hi>that the lauful Paſtoures of Chriſts,
<note place="margin">Heb. 5. Verſ. 4.</note> church ſuld be promoued, &amp; called thair to (tanquam Aaron) as was Aaron.</hi> Bot ye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teſtifieth, that Aaron vvas called to ye dignitie of the Ecceſiaſtical char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge <hi>be ane ordinar vocation, &amp; be ane lauful ſuperiour:
<note place="margin">Leu. 8.</note> for God commanded Moyſes to conſecrat and anoint him, be ane external vnction in the dignitie and office of ane preiſt.</hi> Thairfor al lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Pauſtoures of Chriſts church, ſuld be promoued to the Eccleſiaſtical mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie, be the authoritie of thair lauful Superioures, vvha promoueth thame be ane external vnction, and impoſition of thair hands: And vvha ſendeth tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150570:19"/>vvith pouer and iuriſdiction, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut thair charge in ſik pairtes, as ar ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to thair autoritie: Bot nather Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin nor the miniſters of his ſect, vvas promoued to ye miniſtrie be ane lauful ſuperiour: Thairfor thay ar nocht lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſtoures of Chriſts treu church. Of ſuch extraordinar teachers our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueour forſpak ſuld cum in the latter dayes,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7. Verſ. 15.</note> 
               <hi>nocht ſend, but ſuld intrud tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſelfes, climming ouer the dyk in Chriſts shipfald to deuor his ſlok, with ye bloodie teeth of thair hereſies, being cled with shipkynnes,</hi> that is to ſay, vvith the ſoft habite of the external vvords of the ſcriptures, but tane in ane fals ſenſe;
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> 
               <hi>as ſath an alledged ye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures aga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Chriſt.</hi> Thairfor <hi>Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to be war with thame, as theu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es &amp; throtcutters.</hi> So no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can haue iuſt excuſe of thair auin perdition; being deceaued be thame, throght the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of the veritie ſeing thay commit thame ſelfes to vulauful teachers, vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth expreſlie to eſcheu,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150570:19"/>as theues and throtcutters. And becaus thir miniſters hath nocht in thair prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended church vniuerſalitie of perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; for thay can nocht shau ane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual ſucceſsion of lauful paſtoures, deſcending from the Apoſtles: Zea thay ar ſchamed of thair patriarch Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, teaching contrarious doctrine to his: Thairfor thay haue nocht Chriſts treu church, vvhich is vniuerſal, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of vniuerſalitie of perſones: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue thay vniuerſalitie of places, or of tymes: Thairfor thair co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenticle, is nocht Chriſts catholik church.</p>
            <p>The aught conſideration is that vvha hath conioyned thame ſelfes to this particuler ſect of Caluin and of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ar in ye vvay of thair damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: becaus thay ar out of the treu church of Chriſt Ieſus vvhich is holie, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal; and conſequentlie, thay haue nather Chriſt for thair head, nor his holie ſpirit for thair inſtructeur. Of this it folloueth alſo, that thair ex poſition of the ſcriptures, is nather of Chriſt nor
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150570:20"/>of his holie ſpirit: Thairfor vvhat thay cal veritie, it is plane hereſie: And vvhat thay cal licht, is verie darknes, Sa thay incurre this curs of God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunced agans ſik fals Prophetes: <hi>VVo be to zou wha calleth darknes licht,
<note place="margin">Iſay. 5.</note> &amp; licht darknes.</hi> Be ye contrair, ſeing ye Roman church is both holie, and alſo catholik or vniuerſal, (as vve haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be manifeſt ſorptures:) Thairfor the members thairof ar the members of Chriſt Ieſus, and in the vvay of thair ſaluation; and hauing ye treu church; thay haue Chriſt Ieſus for thair head; &amp; his holie ſpirit for thair inſtructeur: for this cauſe, <hi>wa beliueth, as ye Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man church beliueth, and wha recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the expoſition of the ſcriptures thairof,</hi> concerning the doctrine of the ſacraments: the inuocation of ſantes, purgatorie, and al controuerſed heades in maters of religiou, ar aſſured, that thay erre nocht in thir &amp; vvther heades of thair ſaluation; Becaus ye doctrine of this church, is the doctrine of Ieſus
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150570:20"/>Chriſt, and of his halie ſpirit. This is ye onlie treu reul to decerne veritie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that bringeth to ſaluation, from the hypocriſie of errours and hereſies of malignant churches, that leadeth to perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from the vvhich, God reduce al deceaued Chriſtians, and bring tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to ye motherlie beſome of Chriſts treu church, vvhich is decerned from the malignant churches of deceatful haeretiks, in ſa far as it is holie, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik, Apoſtolik, and Roman, out of the vvhich thair is na ſaluation. For out of Chriſt Ieſus thair is no ſaluation: Bot vvha ar out of the treu church of God, vvhich I haue prouin to be holie, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik, Apoſtolik, and Roman, ar out of Chriſt Ieſus: Ergo out of the treu church of God, vvhich is holie, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik, Apoſtolik and Roman thair is na ſaluation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
